Theme Tune: [music playing]
Al: Hello farmers and welcome to another episode of The Harvest Season. My name is Al
Chelsea: My name is Chelsea.
Al: and we're here today to talk about cottagecore games. Woo!
Chelsea: Woo!
Al: Hello Chelsea, welcome back. I mean maybe you should be welcoming me back because you were on
Chelsea: Welcome back to you.
Al: multiple episodes while I was off.
Chelsea: Yeah, it's been a while. Welcome back, Al.
Al: Yes, I'm just checking. The last episode I recorded was on the 11th of July.
Al: So that is six weeks. So I've not podcasted for six weeks. So let's see if I can remember how to do it.
Chelsea: We've missed you!
Al: Oh dear. Good fun. Well, thank you all for your recordings and episodes for bug month and
Al: beyond, I guess, because you did last week's as well. They were enjoyable to edit and listen to.
Al: Great! Well, this episode, we are...
Al: We're going to talk about a game that I've been playing for ages and haven't really played
Al: for the last six weeks because I was meant to record it five weeks ago, but then things
Al: happened so I ended up not being able to record it sadly. But we're finally here. Let's see
Al: if I can remember everything about the game before we talk about it. And that is Moonlight
Chelsea: [laughter]
Al: Peaks. So I have played Moonlight Peaks. Chelsea has played Moonlight Peaks. We'll get into
Al: to the details of that in the main section.
Al: That's the word I'm looking for. Before that, we have some news. Despite there being so
Chelsea: [laughs]
Chelsea: Yes.
Al: much news that you had to cover last week, there is more news. It never ends. It does
Chelsea: It never ends.
Al: pause sometimes, especially around December. All that happens around December is delays.
Chelsea: Hmm.
Chelsea: [laughs]
Al: But before all that, Chelsea, what have you been up to?
Chelsea: Well, since last week,
Chelsea: [laughs]
Chelsea: not a whole lot, just been playing some Moonlight Peaks,
Chelsea: playing some Neopets,
Chelsea: this is our daughter's birthday,
Al: Woo!
Chelsea: so my husband was off for the week,
Chelsea: so we did museums, water parks,
Chelsea: get-togethers,
Chelsea: and then it's my son William's birthday on Wednesday,
Chelsea: so we're gonna just keep going,
Chelsea: and then the week after that is school.
Chelsea: [laughs]
Al: Wow.
Chelsea: So we're just trying to shove that last little bit of summer
Al: Yeah.
Chelsea: at the end, because they start on the 2nd of September,
Chelsea: which means back to routine, kinda.
Al: When, how long, how long is your summer holidays?
Chelsea: [laughs]
Chelsea: So, usually it starts, like, last week of June.
Chelsea: June. We went right up to like
Chelsea: the 28th I think this year of June and then we start September 2nd. So about two months. Yeah,
Al: Wow, that's very long.
Chelsea: how about over there? Okay, I think it'd be beneficial for everybody if they kind of had
Al: Yeah, we get six weeks here.
Chelsea: shorter summer break with more kind of like March break, Christmas break, pauses throughout the year.
Al: - Yeah, yeah, that's nine weeks you get there.
Al: That's a long, a long time.
Chelsea: It's a little long. Yeah, it is.
Al: I definitely prefer, I mean,
Al: you'll experience this as well,
Al: I definitely prefer shorter holidays
Al: because the routine change can be
Al: quite difficult for my children.
Chelsea: For sure. Yeah, we have one starting 11th grade, 8th grade, 7th grade, and 4th grade.
Chelsea: So, three of the four are at one school this year, and one is just on her own for two more years.
Al: No, no.
Chelsea: But, no, it's good. They're not scattered everywhere anymore.
Chelsea: Yeah, so that's parenting. What have you been up to? Well, what I've been up to is what my children have been up to.
Al: Yeah. Nice. Well, not much longer until you can have some break during the day. Yes, absolutely.
Chelsea: But no, it's been a good summer.
Chelsea: Well, more Moonlight Peaks time.
Chelsea: My Animal Crossing island's been neglected too.
Al: Shocking. Shocking. I have also been playing Moonlight Peaks since
Al: since I was last on the episode but again that's it's been quite a while so it's not really been
Al: the last couple of weeks. Although I do have it open next to me just so I can confirm anything
Al: that I have to question. What I have been playing is I have picked up Rhythm Heaven Groove.
Al: So that's the new Rhythm Heaven game. I don't know if you've played. Oh here's a fun thing.
Al: I can't remember which name is which because the name is different here than it is in North America.
Al: One of them calls it Rhythm Heaven.
Chelsea: Oh.
Al: And one of them calls it Rhythm Paradise.
Al: And I can never remember which is which.
Chelsea: Okay.
Chelsea: Oh, I'm not sure.
Chelsea: I think, yeah, you've mentioned it before.
Al: Because the problem is that all of the stuff I see online is one name, but then Craig calls
Al: it the other name, because that's the only name he knows is the name that's on the thing.
Al: And so I've got to the point where I just can't remember what it's called.
Chelsea: Wait a minute. Yeah, you're enjoying that one?
Al: Yes, I am enjoying that.
Al: It's good fun.
Al: I haven't got through as much as I would have liked to, but I'll get there.
Al: And then I also picked up in the last week or.
Al: So the POCOPIA DLC so I'm playing through bubbly basin and may or may not have stuff to talk about that in a future episode.
Chelsea: Oh, yes, yes, we should.
Al: All right, should we get on with some news then.
Al: First up cozy grove camp spirit, this is the most recent cozy grove game, which was previously on netflix.
Al: It is now also out on steam and on switch and I just realized.
Chelsea: On Netflix?
Al: Yeah, so it was a netflix game originally.
Chelsea: Okay, I have not delved into any Netflix games.
Al: And it's not too bad, it's I guess the main disadvantage is that obviously it's not on consoles or anything so it's kind of designed around phone slash TV, I guess, but so it's yeah.
Al: Now, obviously, I'm--
Al: I'm never a huge fan of when things are exclusive to a subscription service.
Al: That's not great.
Chelsea: I'm not a cheating service.
Al: Yeah, yeah, exactly.
Al: It is also on Xbox and PlayStation.
Al: I'd just forgotten to check that before.
Al: So, yeah, Cozy Grove Camp Spirit is now out on wherever you play games,
Al: unless that's some weird old console.
Chelsea: I had to laugh there's um in Canada we have Rogers TV and in like the mid-2000s
Chelsea: you could do picture-in-picture and you could play it like a bubble blast game
Chelsea: while you're watching TV and I'm like this is the future the future is now
Al: ah yes yeah we had that yeah we had that as well um on on ours here that was a good fun enjoyed that
Chelsea: crazy oh my goodness yeah
Al: uh next up star birds um have announced that their 1.0 is coming out in 2027 uh sorry to
Al: kevin who had that on his game draft for this year uh you're not getting points for that one
Chelsea: [laughs]
Al: well not this year because you know so we shall see
Al: end up winning but if if kevin it well yeah I mean that'll be high up on the list won't it for the
Chelsea: You won 2027.
Al: 2027 draft also coming out in 2027 is Neverway which has been delayed it was meant to be coming
Chelsea: Oh, it could still be April.
Chelsea: You never know.
Al: out this year but before that it was meant to be coming out last year so they're on a run of delaying
Al: let's see if it actually comes out next year
Chelsea: We get GTA 6 before, never wait.
Al: I BELIEVE THIS GAME WAS-
Al: [Continues to talk about the game being released in the UK]
Chelsea: Oh my goodness, it's an urban legend at this point.
Chelsea: It gets to the point where you just lower your expectations and then be pleasantly surprised when it does eventually.
Al: My bad, I'm talking about a different game. This one was never meant to be coming out in 2025.
Al: That would have been Witchbrook. There we go. I'm mixing things up in my head here.
Chelsea: Oh, okay.
Al: Witchbrook has not as of now been delayed to 2027 but doesn't have a release date yet. Their most
Al: recent update was like "oh we're still going" and people are like "okay yeah yeah you're gonna
Chelsea: We're still here.
Al: release this year" or because they - yes I think it was Witchbrook that was originally announced
Chelsea: they'll do a silk song and be like, "yep, prepare yourself, it's ready."
Al: Oh, it's way worse than I was saying. Witchbrook was originally announced in 2016. It's even
Chelsea: Oh my goodness, is this their first game?
Al: changed name since then. It was originally Spellbound and is now Witchbrook. It's Chucklefish
Al: I believe who are actually developing it, because they were originally just a games
Al: publisher. They published Stardew before it went self-published. But it looks like it's
Al: their first game? Good question. I don't think so. No, it is not their first game. This will
Chelsea: Not even trying to be rude, like, is this your first game?
Chelsea: Not- no sass required.
Al: be their fourth game. Oh, they actually developed the Wargroove games. I don't know if you're
Al: Wargroove 2 came out a couple of years ago. It was like a big, it's a turn-based tactics
Al: game, but it was like.
Al: Quite heavily marketed by Nintendo, I think.
Chelsea: Okay.
Al: But yes, and they also released a game called Starbound, which I had never heard of.
Al: So yeah, no, it's their fourth game, but Starbound, their first game,
Al: came out the year they announced this game, Witchbrook.
Al: So they've released three games since they've announced this game.
Chelsea: [laughs]
Chelsea: The magnum opus.
Al: Yeah, but no, I think their biggest.
Al: Thing would have been publishing Stardew Valley looking through the list. I'm not seeing anything even in the publishing. I don't see anything else. It's anywhere near as big. So wonder how much money they made from publishing that probably a decent amount.
Chelsea: Um, enough to fund this game.
Al: Well, exactly. That's that money won't last forever, considering they're no longer the publisher, but it's clearly enough to let them do some stuff, which is always nice.
Al: Next up, Japanese Rural Life Adventure have announced their 1.3 point.
Al: Yes, yeah, I like the look of it. It's in the bucket of I sure would like to play this at some point, but I don't think it's going to be prioritized above most of the other games I'm playing. So will I ever actually get to it? Who knows?
Chelsea: That's a cute art style.
Chelsea: I don't know a ton about this game.
Chelsea: If the circumstances were as such as if we could play this game, would love to do that
Al: It has been reviewed
Al: Very well, it's very positive on steam. So
Chelsea: one day!
Al: Well, I wish I had infinite time to play infinite games, but sadly we do not
Al: Next up cult of the lamb in
Al: Possibly their weirdest update yet have released a two-point museum collab
Al: This is a free update and they say that's right
Al: The lamb is going on a field trip curate your followers earn devotion and perform rituals for your very own
Al: Museum cult in the latest update for two-point museum
Al: Follow in the teachings of Ratao the hallowed ground which was was his is now yours build a shrine to demonstrate your faith
Al: Gather delicious devotion and gather your followers by your hand
Al: Our cult will grow more powerful than any could have imagined
Al: And I just realized based on that that makes it sound like the update is actually in
Al: Two-point museum, but I was I thought the update was in cult of the lamb
Chelsea: Yeah, I don't- I'm confused, because I'm reading it, and I'm like, "Wait, which one?"
Al: Hmm. I think this actually... yeah, okay, so this is not in Cult of the Lamb, this is in Two-Point Museum.
Chelsea: Okay, okay, yeah, that, yeah, that's no clarification there.
Al: So, there we go.
Chelsea: Side note, they have a board game coming out for Call to the Lamb.
Al: They do, yes.
Chelsea: Very cool! Oh, Kickstarter, of course. Very cool.
Al: Yeah, the Cult of the Lamb stuff in Two Point Museum does look very Cult of the Lamb-y,
Al: it's quite nicely translated to the 3D art style they have,
Al: but keeping the kind of, you know, feel of Cult of the Lamb, I feel.
Chelsea: I thought it might have been hard to translate over, but maybe not.
Al: Well, hard doesn't mean they can't succeed.
Chelsea: Well, no, maybe. Expectations subverted.
Al: Yeah, so if you want your own museum cult, go play Two Point Museum.
Al: We also have four new games to talk about. There are actually more games than this that
Al: are on my list of new games because, my goodness, the summer is a long time when you're
Al: away for six weeks, but I'm only going to cover four in this episode because that is,
Al: in and of itself, a lot of games to cover in the new games section.
Chelsea: Yeah, but me and Kevin might have to do another update news catch-up.
Al: Yeah, we'll see, we'll see. If I manage to fit all the other ones into the next week and there's
Al: no other new new games, then we'll be fine, but we shall see. So first up, Focus Grove. Focus Grove
Al: is a work companion that grows with your progress, build your farm, use productivity tools and unlock
Al: new content by completing your real-life tasks, improve your focus, well-being and work-life
Al: balance. So this is a Rusty-like, as we call it, which is a game that plays on the
Al: bottom part of your screen while you do other things.
Chelsea: I can't do it.
Al: Yeah, well, it's a very specific kind of game for its very specific kind of person.
Chelsea: As cute as it looks.
Al: Let's put it that way.
Chelsea: I'm an all-in-- oh, I see. Okay, I see.
Chelsea: Like, you set your own timers and stuff.
Al: Yes, yes, so the idea is that this ties in with to-do lists and notepads and I think
Al: he's got a Pomodoro timer and stuff like that and so the idea is you grow things by
Al: doing your tasks etc so it's trying to be a productivity tool. Maybe, maybe you can
Chelsea: Oh, okay. Maybe then. Maybe I'm in.
Chelsea: Maybe I'm in.
Al: just make fake tasks. This is always my problem with these things it's like oh
Al: great so I can just lie to myself.
Chelsea: That's the thing, like, I can- I'm not holding myself accountable.
Al: Yeah, yeah. Stand up, tick.
Chelsea: Yeah, I totally did that task in this time, to get my reward. What are you talking about?
Chelsea: Tick!
Al: Scroll tick-tock, tick.
Chelsea: Yeah, oh my gosh. Okay, well, yeah, I can see how this could help not me.
Al: The list of features Pomodoro Timer, Task Tracker, Ambient Nature Sounds for better focus, Habits Tracker, Notepad with tabs,
Al: Relaxing No Stress Farming, Cute Woodly...
Al: Woodling? I assumed that would have been Woodland, but it says Woodling. Cute Woodling Companions, Tips from Personal Growth Trainer,
Al: Work Statistics, Fishing Album,
Al: Adjustable Tools Layout, and
Al: Gentle growth reminders my actual real problem with these games
Al: Things that integrate with a to-do list is they never integrate with my existing to-do list
Al: So why am I going to like?
Al: Create my to-do list in a game when I already have my to-do list that is on my phone on all my devices
Al: Set up exactly the way I want it
Al: You've got to integrate with third-party to-do lists if you want me to ever do anything with this
Chelsea: You think so, right? But this way you can get your cute woodland companions
Chelsea: But yeah, it would be handy to just be able to like export from an app you already use
Al: But it doesn't even need to export these things have APIs right like connect to my existing thing
Al: And then when I take off in my existing app it just goes into the game that would be good to please and thanking you
Al: I
Al: Guess the problem is it's probably designed towards people who don't already have to-do lists and stuff like that, but
Chelsea: i'm just picturing a government worker like putting their important list on here
Chelsea: and then there's some privacy breach in focus grove whoops
Al: Yeah, yeah, there was one way
Al: I don't know whether you listen to this episode or not Chelsea
Al: but there was one where.
Al: It was based ...things grew based on how much you typed on the keyboard.
Al: And the problem with that is that it knows exactly which key you're pressing.
Al: So it's a keylogger.
Al: Like it gets your passwords.
Chelsea: Oh my gosh...
Al: Like, obviously, there's a high chance that they're not storing any of that.
Al: But like, there's a lot of trust in that, right?
Al: Like I, I don't really want.
Chelsea: Yeah. Here's my banking info. Cute idea in theory.
Al: Yeah, exactly.
Al: Like, I don't really want us to.
Al: Yeah, no, thank you.
Al: Um, yes, in theory.
Al: Next up, Island Farmer.
Al: Arrange the farm islands and see your archipelago expand.
Al: Just swap the blocks of a 3D jigsaw puzzle.
Al: So this is a little block-based farming game where you put things together to build up
Al: an island with crops and trees and water, houses, etc.
Chelsea: etc. Yeah.
Al: Farms are set up in islands over calm and clear water in this tiny fantasy experience
Al: that's easy to do and very relaxing, just like a 3D jigsaw puzzle.
Al: Carefully observe the island, try to memorize it, then shuffle the blocks, swap blocks.
Al: Swap blocks to reproduce the desired island and it will compose the archipelago.
Al: Yeah, no, I don't want this.
Al: That's suddenly very much put me off.
Al: I don't want this to be a has to be in a specific.
Chelsea: that's great yeah for oh and turn the camera no no no so i'm
Chelsea: watching the trailer turn the camera zoom in and out and memorize the puzzle
Chelsea: no i'm not doing that but love that for people who would like that
Al: Like, I suspect the early ones are, you know,
Al: quite easy to do, right?
Al: Because it's like, oh, well, obviously that needs
Al: to go there 'cause it just needs to be a farm, right?
Al: But like, then, yeah, no.
Al: There's gonna be more complicated ones.
Al: I can't memorize all that.
Al: Sorry.
Chelsea: I'm getting overwhelmed just looking at this trailer.
Al: I like the idea of this if it was just like,
Al: oh, try and get to like an efficient farm
Al: or, you know, try and make it nicely laid out.
Al: and then you could do something and be happy with it.
Al: But the fact that it's like,
Al: no, you have to get the specific blocks
Chelsea: No, yeah, if they were to say like, "3 grass, 2 dirt, like, configure it how you want, maybe?"
Al: Yeah
Chelsea: Yeah, no.
Chelsea: I don't know, I stru-
Al: But that is also out now, if that sounds like your jam
Chelsea: We sold it so well!
Al: We'd look someone out there is like this is absolutely my jam because I am a jigsaw master
Al: And I like farming and therefore this is what I want
Chelsea: Yeah, no, there's someone, something out there for everyone.
Al: I also think the problem is that it doesn't have
Al: the fatal flaw this has with
Al: compared with jigsaws is
Al: It's not you can't be certain you put it in the right place until you've put everything down
Al: Whereas with jigsaws they click together and you're like, oh, yeah
Al: that's clearly together and like the the image is clearly matching up and stuff like that's what it's like here you're like
Al: Oh, well, this farming thing goes next to this farming thing
Al: But there's six different farming things here and they all look identical which one
Al: Goes where and like it's not it's it doesn't work the same way as a jigsaw does
Chelsea: Yeah
Chelsea: Jigsaw like
Al: jigsaw a it did say
Al: like a jigsaw but yeah I think I think it misses the advantages that jigsaws have
Chelsea: Yeah, the instant, "Yes, you did it!" or "No, it's wrong."
Al: yeah next up
Chelsea: See, if you want to force yourself to play that game, you can just put that with your
Chelsea: Focus Grove and say, "I played 30 minutes of Island Farmer!"
Al: I don't tend to want to play games because I feel I have to I know that's complicated because
Al: I have this podcast and so certain people would probably debate me on that but generally I like
Al: I like to play games because I enjoy it.
Al: Generally.
Chelsea: I got to lock in on Island Farmer for this podcast.
Al: [laughs]
Al: Next up, Spiritstead.
Al: That is such a generic thing.
Al: [laughs]
Al: Description.
Al: What I will say is that the...
Al: The visuals are very interesting. It almost looks hand-drawn, kind of cartoony hand-drawn
Al: type thing. It is quite bright, yeah. Trying to describe this is hard.
Chelsea: It is very, very bright.
Chelsea: It's almost like 90s anime, but in a different color scheme? I don't know how to explain this, but it's not quite-- I don't know.
Chelsea: Google image it, guys.
Al: You don't even need to do that, link's in the show notes.
Chelsea: Well, there you go.
Al: However, I can't decide if I like the look of this game.
Al: I think it looks quite pretty,
Al: but I don't know if I want my game to look like this.
Al: Everything seems just slightly too small and far away
Al: for me to be able to truly enjoy what I'm looking at.
Chelsea: that's true if you don't have the option to zoom in a little bit you're kind of looking at the whole page the whole time
Al: Yeah, it almost just feels like a
Al: painting rather than a game.
Chelsea: Yeah, it'd be cute if maybe the cutscenes were this style and then you could manipulate
Chelsea: it a bit easier when you're actually playing it, but I don't think it changes.
Al: No, the trailer doesn't seem to actually show gameplay, it just shows like a time-lapse of
Al: the village being put together. So I can't be certain exactly how it actually works gameplay-wise.
Chelsea: There's fishing, there's fishing, yeah.
Al: There's fishing, just what we want.
Chelsea: Yeah, looking through the photos, it's,
Chelsea: yeah, it is super zoomed out the whole time.
Chelsea: So I think that's how it just is.
Al: Yeah and in terms of like everything else, the graphics is the most interesting thing
Al: about this game. Everything else looks kind of pretty generic town builder. With also
Chelsea: Yeah, everything. Then you get your- it does, it does.
Al: for some reason a first person fishing mini game. I feel so out of place there.
Al: Well, there you go. That is also out now. Finally, speaking of city builders,
Al: neighborhoods, which drove me insane for a while because I kept spelling it wrong because
Al: spelling. Neighborhoods is a cozy city sim where you shape streets to help people thrive,
Chelsea: I know, there's a U!
Al: gather and develop strong opinions about a particular bench.
Al: We are reimagining the city builder as a city fixer.
Chelsea: Unreal description.
Al: Yes, so this also has an interesting graphics. It almost looks like clay.
Chelsea: - Yeah, it does, yeah, it does.
Al: Like, it's very interesting looking.
Al: And I would love to know how they made it look like this.
Al: Because it really does just look like, you know, an Aardman animation.
Chelsea: Yeah that's really- I'm just watching the trailer kind of surprised but yeah you're right it looks like a- like a almost stop-motion clays
Al: But the animations they have down as well, it all looks like it's stop-motion, which is very interesting.
Chelsea: It is.
Al: Sadly, I think that's the most interesting thing about this game.
Al: [laughs]
Al: I feel like I've heard that before!
Chelsea: Oh, well, release date to be announced, so we cannot make our verdict just yet.
Al: Yeah, to be announced, and it is coming to Early Access, so, you know, insert your opinions about Early Access.
Al: Cities are living things, sometimes in desperate need.
Al: Desperate need of some life-saving care, design blocks with plants, murals, lights, pocket
Al: parks, bike lanes and other small civic miracles. Cultivate local businesses so they can provide
Al: groceries, shopping, activities and that tragic necessity of capitalism, jobs.
Al: Tend to neighbours so they can be happy where they live. Live somewhere they can afford
Al: and afford to stay long enough to put down roots. Make choices and watch as different
Al: blocks take on their own identities, from the fun-loving block party host to the member.
Al: I do find it funny that they say jobs is the
Al: tragic necessity of capitalism. Now, I'm not going to be a defender of capitalism,
Al: but other societies and ways of organising your society also generally require jobs.
Al: Right, like that's just a society thing. Like, people doing things is generally needed for
Chelsea: The capitalism of hospitals.
Al: a society. How you want to describe that does depend on your organisation of that society,
Al: but it still generally requires people doing things.
Chelsea: Yes, oh
Chelsea: My goodness. I feel like the mayor of my city needs to play this game
Chelsea: Because they have this idea of 15 minute
Chelsea: Like neighborhoods or what? Yeah, so that we don't need public transit and stuff and it's just not working
Al: Yep, no, that's not the point of 15-minute cities, is not not needing public transport.
Al: That's not the point.
Chelsea: Oh, well, run for mayor of my town, Al, please.
Al: I feel like they have completely misunderstood what the point of it is.
Al: It's like we have two different people misunderstanding 15-minute cities.
Al: The people who think it's, for some reason, a communist plot.
Chelsea: [laughs]
Al: Which, I'm just gonna say this, those people are insane.
Al: But I've never heard this one
Al: before. This is an interesting one. So they think that because 50 minute cities, the point
Al: generally is that everything that you need on a daily basis is within 15 minutes walk
Al: where you live. That doesn't mean we don't need public transport.
Chelsea: yes i'm gonna i'm gonna add this in the show notes because it's such a debate in our city
Al: What?
Chelsea: like well so it's crazy I can't even explain the debacle going on
Al: I just, I don't understand that concept. Because like, yeah, just because you live
Al: somewhere where you can access all the things you need on a daily
Al: basis within 15 minutes, doesn't mean you never want to go anywhere else.
Chelsea: Exactly. So they're like, oh, well, to discourage parking lots and maximize space, including
Chelsea: public transit, let's just walk everywhere and then you're good. You need your grocery
Al: but okay but okay but like if they're trying to discourage car parks which I think is a laudable
Chelsea: store, your pharmacy, your clinic. That's it. That's all you need for society. That's
Al: goal uh you kind of need the public transport for that you know like do they do they think
Chelsea: kind of. Yeah, and well, yeah, because we try we have a big LRT
Al: that people are just never going to leave their 15-minute area is that what they're thinking?
Chelsea: system that was supposed to be built in 2018. It's 20 almost
Chelsea: 2027 and we have one part of one area of the town and it was made
Chelsea: by a company that this is such a weird tangent. It was made by a
Al: No, no go for it
Chelsea: company that only is proficient in warm weather.
Chelsea: And so half of our winter. Yeah, in Ottawa, where it's freezing and wet. So the line is down half the time, and it's just, oh my I can't. Yeah, I'm putting this in the show notes, please just look at the infrastructure plan for Ottawa because it's a disaster.
Al: Ah, in Canada.
Al: Yes, please do, please do.
Al: I will link that in the show notes.
Al: It's just this absolutely fascinating,
Al: like it's such a misunderstanding of the whole concept.
Al: Also, one thing I find that people seem
Al: to misunderstand quite often is they think that,
Al: they seem to think that the 15-minute cities
Al: is like self-contained, like you can only go
Al: within your own, like the 15-minute city is not like,
Al: here's this 15-minute city, here's this 15-minute city,
Al: here's this 15-minute city.
Al: It just means that like everyone has the things
Al: they need within 15 minutes of themselves,
Al: but that doesn't mean it's all for like,
Al: all the same place, right?
Al: Like it doesn't mean that like, here's a 15-minute circle,
Al: it has all of the things in it,
Al: and then everyone on the edges has to go to the middle.
Al: It's like, no, you can go to a different one, right?
Al: It just means that everyone can have those things
Al: within 15 minutes of themselves.
Al: It's like how the capitalist version of this
Al: is how McDonald's tried to have.
Al: like no one within a certain distance
Al: farther away from McDonald's within cities, right?
Al: I can't remember what it is.
Al: People say different things, right?
Al: But like the idea is that everybody
Al: is within a certain distance of a McDonald's.
Al: But it doesn't mean that there's a specific McDonald's
Al: that they want you to go to.
Chelsea: [laughs]
Al: You know, that would be insane.
Chelsea: Yeah. Oh yeah, no, I'm adding this in the show notes, 'cause I, yeah.
Chelsea: Sorry, neighborhoods, you got me fired up.
Al: Bizarre, bizarre. So anyway, back to the game, I think it's an interesting idea of, because
Chelsea: Yes.
Chelsea: [laughs]
Al: one of the problems, I guess, of city builders is they're quite, they're greenfield, right?
Al: Like you start off with nothing and then you create a city and it's very, almost the, like,
Al: the capitalist ideal of a city is like, we are going to design a city now. And it's like,
Al: exists and we're going to make it but that's not how
Al: life works most of the time right you have cities generally even in even in
Al: North America cities generally have been built up over a long time some cities
Al: longer than others but they've still generally been built up over you know
Al: hundreds of years and so things just don't you can't you can't just ignore
Al: them right it's like the typical how you know Central Park before it was built in
Al: in New York City, before it was built,
Al: there were neighborhoods there, right?
Al: People lived in those areas and they wanted to make a park,
Al: which is a laudable goal.
Al: But to do that,
Al: they kicked a whole bunch of people out of their houses
Al: who generally happened to be non-white people,
Al: because of course they did.
Al: And so the history of that
Al: is a history of people being displaced.
Al: And so generally you don't just get to look at,
Al: here's a fresh area, we need to build something.
Al: you generally have to look at an existing.
Al: area and say, "How can we improve this?" And I do like the idea that this is trying to focus on that.
Al: That's an interesting idea, and I like the graphics. How it actually ends up doing it
Al: in practice is a question that I don't think we'll have an answer for just now.
Chelsea: I might just play this game out of spite, but no, like it's a good idea.
Chelsea: But yeah, like I said, I living in a, where I live is a personal vendetta
Chelsea: against this kind of thing.
Al: *sniff* Fun times.
Al: Alright, that's our news.
Chelsea: Woo!
Al: Let's talk about Moonlight Peaks.
Al: So I like to start off talking about these games by giving a quick description of them
Al: and then Chelsea can tell me how she thinks I did.
Al: So I would describe this game as "Stardew but vampires" and I think that's all I need
Al: to say.
Chelsea: Yep. That's our show.
Al: [laughs]
Al: I mean obviously there's a lot more to talk about but in terms of like a high level description of a game, I think that is probably the easiest way to sell someone on this game.
Al: Have you wanted to play Stardew but be a vampire? And if the answer is yes then I think I play this game.
Chelsea: - Yes.
Al: [laughs]
Al: Alright, before we get into the details then, Chelsea what do you think of the game overall?
Chelsea: I'm enjoying it, so I'm only 11 hours but I'm a slow player, the thing for me is give
Al: First of all, how much have you played etc etc? Where are you in the game? That sort of stuff.
Chelsea: me a task, and I'm doing it.
Chelsea: So I just, I think I'm 20 some days into the game, and I just unlocked the barn, which
Chelsea: is, because I'm so poor in this game, like, I don't know what I
Chelsea: hope it eases up as you go on, but I've been making, like, wine and stuff, because apparently
Chelsea: that's the big seller at the start.
Chelsea: Anyway, no, I've been enjoying it, I find that there is a lot to do at the start but
Chelsea: it does stall quite a bit to the point where you're just kind of, I'm spending my day
Chelsea: in the mine, not even, I'm like neglecting everybody.
Al: Yeah, yeah. I think you might not be surprised to know that that does continue. I think my
Al: biggest thing about this game that I would say to people is the pacing is very weird.
Al: Some things go really, really slowly and some things absolutely zoom past. And I'm not saying
Al: it's necessarily a bad thing, but because part of the thing about these games is...
Al: The monotony of them is...
Al: Well, it's a benefit, right? It's why we play these games, because we like the monotony.
Chelsea: you know, the predictability of your day.
Al: We like the mindless farming. That's one of the things that people like.
Chelsea: Yeah, I honestly thought at the start, I thought I missed a big
Chelsea: part of the beginning because I'm like, is this what I'm
Chelsea: supposed to do? And that may have just been me, but I think
Al: Yeah, yeah.
Chelsea: you're right with the pacing because some of it I've done so
Chelsea: many character stories already. And then other days, I'm just in
Chelsea: the mine, processing iron.
Al: Yeah, yeah, yeah
Al: Well, I mean, so yeah
Al: So there's I think there's two examples that I'll use just now before we get into the details of why I think the pacing is
Al: off
Al: First up is in the mine
Al: You don't get gold in the mine until very late in the game
Al: Like I was nearly done. I was nearly done the story when I unlocked the ability to get gold
Al: because the way, and that's going to be the case.
Al: for anyone, because the places in the mine that have gold are unlocked through story progression
Al: rather than independent of that story progression. And for some reason they're quite, well,
Al: so there's a first part that unlocks, I feel like it's maybe like 60% through the story,
Al: you unlock transformations, right? You can, because you, have you unlocked the first transformation?
Chelsea: Well, I'm a cat, yeah. I did that, like, really early.
Al: yes yeah yeah so you are you you can yeah so you can have three
Al: transformations in this game is actually one of the things I really like about this game is the transformation so you
Al: can you first of all have the ability to transform into a cat
Al: and that allows you to run really fast and there's like a few areas you can get to because you're smaller now
Al: and stuff like that but then there are two other transformations you get
Al: which the first one unlocks an area in the mine that has
Al: On most days, maybe one gold.
Al: And then the third transformation gets you to an area that has more gold in it, but that is basically the end of the story, what the transformations are.
Chelsea: It does. It does.
Chelsea: Okay, I'll ask at the end if you don't want to spoil it.
Chelsea: Yeah, I know. I think I know what the third one is, but I won't, I won't say it now.
Al: Do you know what the second one is?
Chelsea: Is one of them water related?
Al: Yes.
Chelsea: Okay.
Chelsea: Then I don't know what one of the other one is.
Al: I'll maybe, I'll put it, let me add it to the show notes. I'll add it near the end. We'll have a little spoilers section at the end where we can, we can talk about it.
Chelsea: Okay, okay
Chelsea: Yeah, cuz I've been on that Moonlight Peaks reddit and there's probably no nothing surprising me anymore
Al: Yeah, no you probably are. We'll get to that, we'll get to that, we'll get to that.
Chelsea: Cuz I was looking I'm like I have to be missing something. What am I doing? But yeah
Al: So that's one of the things I found really weird is gold is really hard to come by until
Al: you've basically finished the story. And secondly, there is a greenhouse that you can get in
Al: this game, but you get it through completing, by getting the museum to 80% completion. And
Al: first up, you probably don't even know there's a museum, you probably not even, well you
Al: You might know it because you've seen it somewhere,
Al: but you've not unlocked a museum yet.
Chelsea: I have not unlocked the museum. I know I saw people raving about the update for that.
Al: Because, because you get the museum through the story,
Al: and it's like maybe like 50% of the way through the story
Chelsea: Yeah.
Al: before you unlock the museum.
Al: And then you have to get it to 80%
Al: before you unlock the greenhouse,
Al: which is just such a bizarre idea.
Al: Like, I understand the idea
Al: that you don't get the greenhouse very early on
Al: because it's, you know, a very powerful thing to get,
Al: but 80% museum completion?
Chelsea: Yeah, I was expecting, like, an Animal Crossing, like, "Oh, Blathers is here!"
Al: Mad!
Chelsea: I was like, "Ooh, is there going to be a new person to open up this?"
Chelsea: I thought maybe it was the, like, Luna?
Al: So that does happen, you do get more people and that will lead you to the story part where
Al: you open the museum. I just find it really weird that there's 80%, like I have completed
Al: the game and I'm at 60% completion in the museum. Oh definitely shouldn't be selling
Chelsea: So, I shouldn't have been selling my fish.
Al: your fish. Such, I just, some of the pacing is just really weird. I don't, but I also,
Chelsea: Oh no.
Al: I got to the point where, and they've actually nerfed this in an update, is that I
Al: got to a point where I was making a lot of money, very kind of medium game. They nerfed
Chelsea: They nerfed it?
Al: it. They've reduced the price of wine and stuff like that, which is very annoying. And
Al: I'm like, I don't feel like that solves your pacing issues. I know what you're trying to
Al: do. It doesn't solve your pacing issues and it just makes people annoyed.
Chelsea: Yeah, because I find already-- I don't know if-- has the update taken place-- yeah, I don't know 'cause, for me, wine, I sell it at $3.60, I think?
Chelsea: Is that after the-- no, yeah, that's after.
Al: - Yeah, the update came out on Friday,
Al: so you've probably been selling at the old price.
Chelsea: Okay, so, I'm not sure but--
Al: I can't remember the exact prices.
Chelsea: yeah.
Al: That's not how my brain works.
Chelsea: Yeah, but I've been-- I feel like I'm so slow because I'm getting all these things and I'm like, "okay, I just got enough to buy the bar."
Al: [laughs]
Al: Yeah, it's an annoying thing for them to do.
Chelsea: Damn.
Chelsea: Like, oh, wow, okay. Yeah, that's...
Al: I understand the theory of balancing your
Al: game after it's released, but the problem is when it's a single-player game, it just
Al: feels petty when you're reducing things.
Chelsea: well that's it like who am I comparing myself to I i can't see anyone I can't compete with anybody like
Al: Yeah. If you want to try and fix your pacing, like, move other things up rather than pulling
Al: things down, right? Make other things better. Or make things more expensive if you must,
Chelsea: Exactly, yeah, like lower the length of crops or something.
Al: right? Like, don't reduce what people can see. Because it just makes it feel rubbish.
Al: Especially as, like, the grapes are repeating crops and the way this game does them is like
Al: repeating crops are essentially infinite until the end of the season, which if you have a
Al: greenhouse is forever. But we'll get to that. We'll get to that.
Chelsea: Okay. That's annoying. That's just petty for the sake of petty, I think.
Al: It is. It is. We'll get to that because I've not had a lot of time to think about that
Al: because that only dropped two days ago, that update. But I'm sure we'll talk about that.
Al: Yeah. So I don't think you've answered the question. How do you enjoy the game? I think
Al: you got to the point of how far you've gotten in. How are you enjoying it so far?
Chelsea: I am enjoying it, but yeah, like we've said, the pacing is really throwing me off, because I feel like I'm so behind, but other parts I feel ahead, because I feel like I've really progressed with some of the characters, but then I'm still waiting for the barn to be built, I'm still getting all these basic tools, I only have the copper, two copper tools, and the rest are still rusty.
Chelsea: I am enjoying it, though. Yeah.
Al: Yeah
Al: Do you know I think actually the I think another issue with the pacing is that
Al: In Stardew if you hit a point in your main story where you're not progressing things
Al: You can then go and like progress the mine because the whole point of that mine is you are
Al: Trying to get to the bottom, right?
Al: so like every day you can go in and do like a five levels and unlock another level on the
Al: The lift to get back down to that whereas this mine is just like a single level
Al: There's nowhere to go
Chelsea: Okay, I wanted to ask in terms of that, is there a way to fast travel?
Al: except
Al: Yes, there is but you won't get it for a long time
Chelsea: Okay, not just as a cat, okay.
Al: There are two ways of fast travel I'll get out. I'll talk about them
Al: I will talk about them. I think later on but there are two ways of fast traveling
Chelsea: Okay, that gives me some hope, because I'm getting frustrated.
Al: But they're not great fast traveling
Chelsea: [laughs]
Chelsea: Okay.
Al: Just I just want to clarify I do like this game
Chelsea: Yes, I- okay.
Al: I'm going to complain a lot about this game as we go through
Chelsea: [laughs]
Al: this podcast episode but I do genuinely like this game. This has been a really good Stardew-like.
Chelsea: It's because we care, that we want it.
Al: Alright, graphics wise, I guess it's kind of, I would describe it as kind of chibi-esque
Al: characters in a shiny 3D world, obviously based on, you know, like a vampire town,
Al: but it's more than vampires, but we'll talk about that later, like a mythical creature's town.
Chelsea: Yeah. Yes.
Al: What do you think about the graphics?
Chelsea: I think they're pretty good. I know that there's a way to change the art style.
Chelsea: Uh, I have not tried it yet.
Al: Oh, oh boy, have you heard the controversy of that?
Chelsea: That's okay. That's a whole other thing.
Chelsea: No. What is it?
Al: Okay, so there is, so yeah, so like with most games, there's the portraits that show up when
Al: you're talking to someone and their art style is a little bit different from the main art style,
Al: right, like all of the characters, the models running around the town are chibi-esque
Al: and the character portraits are.
Al: different. They're much more kind of not realistic, but like more detailed and stuff like that,
Al: less shiny, I would call them. And then there is a second version of the portraits. Now the
Al: real problem, the controversy around the second version of the portraits is, so it's anime style,
Al: but the controversy is that every character that has a, you know, a non-white ethnicity,
Al: you know, there are, there are black characters, there are Asian characters, etc.
Al: All of them, now this is not me saying this because I'm not an expert in these sorts of
Al: things, but a lot of people say that the anime style kind of homogenizes the features of those
Al: characters and means that like traditionally black facial features are not there anymore.
Al: And so it, they all just end up looking kind of anime style, which doesn't have the most
Al: intricacies for, you know, different facial.
Al: features and styles and just a lot of those things end up being, "Oh, it just looks like
Al: generic anime person."
Chelsea: Right, okay, yeah, I heard it was basically, like, a "yassified" version.
Al: Yeah, yeah, that too, that too.
Chelsea: But, like, smoothed over and, yeah, not much diversity.
Al: Exactly, exactly. Like, the characters are obviously still different ethnicities,
Al: it's just that you can only really tell that because of their skin color,
Al: you know, which is not particularly great.
Chelsea: Okay, yeah, yeah, yeah
Chelsea: No
Al: And I suspect is probably why that's kind of hidden away as a setting.
Chelsea: Okay, yeah, they're like, you know what we you can look for it if you want but we're not yeah, I
Al: Yeah, I just, I'm confused as to why they did that at all.
Chelsea: Can't I could not tell you to be honest
Al: Like, "Hey, I want my characters to be less human."
Chelsea: I want my vampire to look less human
Al: Well, it's not even that because there are humans in the game as well and
Chelsea: Yeah
Al: the humans that are in the game are black characters.
Chelsea: Yes
Al: Uh, yeah, I don't know.
Chelsea: Yeah, I don't know they could have done it a little better
Al: Yeah, it's just a bit icky, a bit icky.
Al: Okay, so yeah, I mean, I think I generally agree with you.
Al: I think the overworld graphics are fine.
Al: I don't dislike them, I don't think they're particularly amazing.
Al: I like a lot of kind of the small touches to these things, but
Al: like the character models in the overworld are just kind of fine.
Al: I do think that the general, the main
Al: portraits are quite good. I think the, you know, as we've talked about there is
Al: generally a good diversity within the town on those portraits and yeah the
Al: anime style ones are particularly not great. But if you want to do that then I
Al: guess that's an option you can do. Yeah, yeah. One thing I would say about graphics
Al: is that, so as background for this, one of the things that makes this game unique is
Al: empire, your days are actually nights. So instead of being up during the day, you're
Al: up during the night. And that's an interesting idea, but here's my problem with it, is that
Al: as your day continues, it gets darker and darker, and then it gets lighter and lighter.
Al: So in the middle of the day, it's hardest to see things, which doesn't feel like the
Al: right way around. And I know what's happening, and I know why it's happening. And I'm not
Al: saying it's.
Al: wrong thematically, it just in terms of gameplay, it's not ideal that in the middle of the day,
Al: it's hardest to see.
Chelsea: Right. No, I agree with that. I also love that you sleep in a coffin.
Al: Yes, yes. Well, you're a vampire. Where else are you going to sleep? Actually, it's really
Al: funny because you can have beds. You can get a bed and you put it in your house, but you
Al: can't sleep in them. If you go to interact with them, they go, "Ew, it looks uncomfy."
Al: I just enjoyed that because I was like, "Oh, can I sleep in a bed rather than there?" No,
Chelsea: Hahahahahahahahahahahahahahahahahahahahahahah
Al: you cannot. Also, just a thing that you might encounter at some point, see if you ever fall
Al: asleep or you go, not go to sleep because you can't do it. You can't go to sleep.
Al: normally without interacting with your coffin. But if you were to remove your coffin from
Al: the house, put it in your inventory, and then wait until the point where you auto-sleep,
Al: you wake up confused on the floor because there's no coffin. Anyway, we'll get to all
Chelsea: Ah, that's amazing. I love that. Okay, okay.
Al: those mechanics in a bit. So, let's get to the mechanic details then. I debated so long
Al: and hard about which order to do these in, but I think we need to go with magic first
Al: because the magic.
Al: so many different parts of the game and I think if we, if I get to farming and I'm trying to
Al: explain the magic part of farming, I don't think it makes sense unless I've described magic in
Al: general. Have you unlocked the magic in the game? Okay, good. I presume you just have the
Chelsea: That's a good start. Starting point. Uh, yeah.
Al: dodgy wand, I can't remember what it's called, like the fixed wand, that's what it is. Yeah,
Chelsea: - Yes, I have the fixed wand with one spell.
Chelsea: Thank you very much.
Al: yeah, cool. So, you are a vampire but you are the child
Al: of Dracula and a witch and therefore you are both a vampire and you can also be a magic user,
Al: which means that at some point in the game, quite early on, you unlock the ability to get a wand
Al: and unlock spells. These are different spells that we'll talk about as we go through the different
Al: sections but essentially they work by you have a mana, which is a different kind of energy
Al: than your normal energy.
Al: And each spell has a different mana cost.
Al: And so to use the spell,
Al: you have to have a certain amount of mana.
Al: And then when you do the spell, you use it up.
Al: I quite like what they did with the casting of the spells.
Al: Essentially, it's a little kind of visual mini game
Al: where you, each spell has a specific shape
Al: you have to make out in, like, it's a circle,
Al: but there's like five points on it.
Al: And then there's a point at the top, the bottom,
Al: the right, and the left.
Al: And you have to make a shape between those ones.
Al: So for example, you can fill your watering can
Al: by going from the middle to the right,
Al: to the bottom, to the left, and then back to the middle.
Al: And I think that was it.
Al: And that fills your watering can for you.
Chelsea: Yeah, it was cool how it set up that way.
Al: Yeah, so different spells have different shapes,
Al: which is interesting.
Al: And when you learn them, the spell goes into your book.
Al: So you can always go back and look at what it was, but the ones you use regularly.
Chelsea: Yes. So far I just have one, so I know that one.
Al: Which one is that is that the the watering one?
Chelsea: The watering. Yeah, that's the first one I got. I think that's for everybody because you do the magic crops.
Al: which we'll come to in the farming.
Al: One thing I really don't like about the magic,
Al: every day when you sleep, you regain one mana
Al: and there's no way to increase that.
Al: The only other way to gain mana is making potions
Al: and drinking, or potions are specific foods
Al: and drinking them to gain back your mana.
Al: So you always have to have like a,
Al: if you ever want to do any magic,
Al: specific consumables.
Al: Now there is one that I made that is really nice
Al: and I just kept using that one
Al: 'cause it was quite an easy one to do,
Al: but it just, it doesn't feel great
Al: that there's no way to increase that.
Al: It's like how if every day you woke up,
Al: you only gained a quarter of your stamina,
Al: you'd really struggle to do much, especially early game,
Al: because you'd have to keep making food
Al: to be able to do anything at all,
Al: because there's so little you can do
Al: with a quarter of your stamina.
Al: It's the same sort of thing with the mana.
Al: I just, I would like it to have increased more,
Al: like I feel like, give us less mana,
Al: less max mana to start with,
Al: but allow us, but fully fill it overnight.
Al: Like it just feels weird that it only increases one,
Al: no matter how much you increase your max stamina,
Al: max mana over time,
Al: it still only ever increases one when you sleep.
Chelsea: Yeah, it is a very slow regeneration.
Al: Especially as, for certain things,
Al: it's the only way of doing automation,
Al: blah, blah, blah, you unlock more spells
Al: by buying them in the magic shop.
Chelsea: Oh, haven't done that yet.
Al: It's fine.
Al: Yeah, you'll get there.
Chelsea: I don't have spell money, I just have barn money.
Al: That's, yeah, barn money.
Al: I will say, if you're doing the barn for the story,
Al: that's fine.
Al: Don't, I would say don't invest too much in animals,
Al: 'cause they're not particularly great
Al: money-making things in this game.
Al: I think that's most of the magic stuff.
Al: How many spells are there?
Al: Eight, I think, let me double check.
Chelsea: I think it's 8 or 12.
Al: Yeah, it's 12 different ones, and I.
Chelsea: Oh, okay.
Chelsea: Ooh, do the casting patterns get more difficult?
Al: Not difficult, no, they're just different shapes. I like, some of them are quite nice,
Al: so like the axe one looks, so what, there's one that you can chop down trees automatically,
Al: and it kind of looks like an axe, and there's a pickaxe one, the same, it looks very much like a
Chelsea: Cheers.
Al: pickaxe as you're doing it, which is a bit fun. What I will say, there's one really nice one
Al: for refilling your watering can that I mentioned earlier, which costs no mana to cast, so that's
Al: really nice, so you can use that an infinite number of times.
Al: All right, let's talk about farming then, because that's what we're all here for.
Al: Farming game, we got farming. So most of this farming is pretty standard. You
Chelsea: [laughs]
Chelsea: In theory.
Al: have a seed, you put the seed, you hoe the ground, till the ground, I never
Al: remember the word, you till the ground, you put the seed in, you water it, it
Al: grows. You have a scarecrow, you have different types of crops that need
Al: some crops, you harvest it and that's gone, some crops you harvest it and it
Al: regrows, blah blah blah. All the standard farming game stuff. One thing that's
Al: different is that the watering is not, so if you think about storage watering, you
Al: like water a pea, you press A to water, you move, you press A to water that one,
Al: you move, you press A to water that one. This one works differently and I both
Al: like and dislike it at the same time for different reasons. So the way this works
Al: as you have your watch.
Al: and it waters within a certain radius of where you are, which includes any blocks within that radius.
Al: Which is nice, so you can just hold down the button and keep walking, and it will water everything in front of you as you're going.
Al: So it's not like start, stop, start, stop. It's hold the button and walk, and it can water everything. But,
Al: but, here's my problem with it. It's
Al: quite hard to know whether you've watered the ground or not, fully.
Chelsea: Yep. Yep.
Al: and sometimes you will miss it.
Al: and not notice that you've not fully watered it, you've partially watered it,
Al: not fully watered it, but you don't notice that, and so the next day one of your plants hasn't grown.
Chelsea: Yep, and that's part of the problem of having the peak of the day be the darkest.
Al: Yes, absolutely.
Chelsea: Also, apparently at the start, rain doesn't water them?
Chelsea: Apparently, there was, like, I don't know if this is at the very beginning, but I saw someone say that rain doesn't water your crops, but I don't know if that was...
Al: It doesn't water magic crops but it does water normal crops.
Chelsea: No, okay.
Chelsea: Okay, okay, good to know.
Chelsea: But yeah, I've missed so many, like, "Oh, I'll be able to harvest this in the next day." Nope, it wasn't watered.
Al: frustrating especially as you know I will generally do like big blocks of the same crop
Al: and so then you have one that's not growing the rest of the rest of them and then it just looks
Al: annoying and out of and I'm like I kind of just want to water that one crop for today and then
Chelsea: Yep, fried in your brain.
Al: leave the rest of them so they're all the same but no I don't do that obviously because that
Al: would be stupid but I think about it I consider it because it's very annoying
Al: yeah yeah because my brain is broken that's why
Al: I want to do that so the next thing is there are a different type of crops
Al: called magic crops and these are generally not edible crops but you use
Al: them for getting mana essence which is what you use to then make potions and
Al: stuff like that and either refill your refill your mana stamina or do other
Al: things like you can make get one that like uh I can't even remember any of the
Al: potions i've got them here let me look at them uh we've got uh there's one that allows you to
Al: chop wood without draining your your energy uh there's one for fish instantly biting
Al: uh there's a few others for um not draining your energy there's one
Al: which is called the sunscreen potion says provides protection from the sun
Al: which you might think means that you can stay up later does not mean that
Chelsea: Oh, I was gonna say, oh, the day gets longer?
Al: not it is for one very specific purpose that is a story related thing maybe i'll talk about that at
Chelsea: Oh.
Chelsea: Ah, okay.
Al: the end um so yeah the mana is used for those things um and you can also like there are certain
Al: kinds of food that you can use like there's there's one which is called the what is it the
Al: mana cupcake which um if you make that you it's it gives you two two mana pack per thing and it's
Al: it's quite easy to make, it just only requires.
Al: one of which is the mana essence and one of which is the
Al: what's it called the moon fruit I think it was
Chelsea: Yeah, that's what I have so far. I've been making like the moon juice potion.
Al: yeah so the the mana cupcake is my go-to because it's so quick and easy to make
Al: um so that's how the but the interesting thing about the magic
Al: there's two interesting thing about the magic crops one is that you can't water them normally
Al: So rain doesn't water them and you're watering.
Al: Watering can doesn't water them. What does water them is the magic watering cans.
Al: So that's the first spell you get is the magic watering cans and that is you run
Al: you I think it's - is it two mana it uses up or is it just one? It's one and then
Al: you will get a watering can that goes out and waters a certain number of spots.
Al: As you you can upgrade that spell and eventually and it will give you as I
Al: a look at my game.
Al: So, I'm going to be talking about the game. I'm going to be talking about the game. I'm
Chelsea: Okay, so tell me why I put my well right next to my house and then I look at every other
Chelsea: Guide like don't buy the well
Chelsea: So yeah, good to know that I don't need that right next to there
Chelsea: Yeah. So yeah. No. So that's just taken up a huge spot on my
Al: going to be talking about the game. I'm going to be talking about the game. I'm going to
Chelsea: life. Where I can put my crops. You can destruct it or destroy
Chelsea: it. Yeah, but
Al: as well. So this is basically the main automation for the game.
Al: the magic for the farming. And there are no sprinklers or anything like that. Well,
Chelsea: Well... [laughs]
Al: this is where it gets a bit complicated. So some of the magic crops do different things.
Al: So the general magic crops, they're just the same as normal crops, except you have to magic water
Al: them. But some of them do different things. So for example, there's one that when it gets to a
Al: certain point, if you want to continue growing it, you have to manually water it.
Al: as well. So you have to like fill it with water after it's watered with the magic watering
Al: cans. Because it gives you more mana. The harder to grow magic crops are definitely
Chelsea: Why? *laughs*
Chelsea: Oh, okay. *laughs*
Al: worth it. There's one, and this is the best one in the game, but it's also the most annoying
Al: one. It's called the Gobbler. And when it gets to a certain point, you have to feed
Al: it either a fish or a bug it will say which one so like they'll it'll have a little eye
Al: that says it has a little bug icon or a little fish icon.
Al: And you have to go up to it and give it a fish or a bug
Al: and then it'll close.
Al: So it's like a Venus flytrap, but a fish trap.
Chelsea: Oh, interesting.
Al: You have to do that two days.
Al: And then once you've done it the second day,
Al: it's then fully grown.
Al: Those are incredible because they give you so much mana.
Al: But I did this.
Al: I decided, right, I'm gonna do gobblers.
Al: And I put out a hundred gobblers.
Al: And then I realized when the first one come up,
Chelsea: [dog barking]
Al: I don't have a hundred fish and a hundred bugs.
Al: [laughing]
Al: So I spent like a week hunting for fish and bugs
Chelsea: Oh my god
Al: to try and get these gobblers done.
Al: And I'm like, this was my biggest mistake.
Al: Don't put a hundred gobblers.
Al: There's no need for that.
Chelsea: Now you... you're playing Gobbler Simulator.
Al: Well, yeah, that was all I did for a week.
Al: The good thing is that once I'd done it all,
Chelsea: Oh my goodness.
Al: I had more mana than I could ever want.
Chelsea: Okay.
Al: But, uh, yeah.
Chelsea: That's... I can't... I can't even picture that. That's hilarious.
Al: Learn from my mistakes.
Al: A hundred gobblers is too many.
Chelsea: So it's like ten, you think?
Al: But those ones only grow in one season, so I was like,
Al: I better get as many done as I can, and then, whoopsie.
Chelsea: Oh.
Al: But,
Chelsea: The season's done before I can finish feeding.
Al: this is leading me to the point of,
Al: when I said there are no sprinklers,
Al: that's not technically true,
Al: in that there is a magic crop that acts like a sprinkler.
Al: So, you plant this one,
Al: and then after a couple of days of watering it,
Al: it will then magically water everything around it,
Al: in a 3x3 grid.
Al: So, like a basic sprinkler in most farming games.
Al: Now, this is actually fine.
Al: I don't dislike this.
Al: I think it's actually quite fun,
Al: a different way of doing a sprinkler.
Al: There's two negatives to it,
Al: one of which is that it doesn't do it for the first two days.
Al: Sure, fine, whatever.
Al: That's not the end of the world.
Al: the world. I'll spend a couple of days
Al: watering everything, and then it takes two weeks to grow. So you manually water everything
Al: for two days, and then for 12 days it will automatically water everything. Great. I actually
Al: quite like that. That's not bad. And if you stagger it, then it means that every day you're
Al: going to do a little bit of watering, but most things will be automatically watered.
Al: And then when they're fully grown and you have to harvest them, then other ones will
Al: do it. It's, you know, it's great. Actually, there's a third thing.
Chelsea: Yeah, and a secret third thing.
Al: I'll get to the third thing first. So the third thing is that if you put it next to
Al: a specific other type of plant, it won't water because it's, it's called the weeping wiccan.
Al: And so if you put it next to a, what was it? Was it a forget-me-not maybe? Then it doesn't,
Al: it's not sad anymore. It's happy. And so it won't cry and water all your crops. So you
Al: have to keep it sad. So if you put a specific crop, if you put a specific crop next to it,
Chelsea: Oh my god, I keep it sad.
Al: it becomes happy and doesn't water them. But that's just, that's just something you learn
Al: very quickly that that's a problem.
Al: But the real issue with it is that they only work in one season, they only grow in one season.
Chelsea: Uh... okay. I haven't come across them yet.
Al: So they're a fun idea and I think if they grew in every season I wouldn't be complaining about
Al: the fact there's no sprinklers but the fact that they exist only for one season is really annoying
Al: because you get into this habit of using them and then it's like oh I'm now in autumn I can't
Al: use them anymore. Ah well. And if you haven't focused on upgrading your...
Chelsea: Mm-hmm. Yeah, that's a line.
Al: your watering spell, which costs a lot of money to upgrade it, right, that it does 144 crops,
Al: I think that that last upgrade was like 50,000 or something. It's expensive. Very expensive.
Chelsea: Oh my god
Al: So yeah I think that's another example of their their scaling is just a little bit off.
Al: And I think if the Weeping Wiccan worked in every season I would enjoy the...
Al: It almost feels like... it almost feels like it was a debate in the team of like
Chelsea: yeah this is really weird to have for one season only I don't know but yeah that's a weird choice
Al: do we actually want this to exist or not and the compromise was
Al: we can have it exist but only in one season, you know.
Chelsea: Yeah, and they give you an extra task for the rest of the year.
Al: Yeah especially as like so many of the magic crops just work in every season. Not all of
Al: them but a lot of them do work in every season so it's not like it it would be the only one.
Chelsea: Yeah, that's a choice.
Al: Anyway, it is what it is.
Al: So I think overall the farming's fine.
Al: Obviously, as we've talked about, there's scaling issues
Al: and there's a couple of things with the automation
Al: that I think could be improved, but overall it's fine.
Al: There's a lot of, so there's things like the kegs
Al: that make wine and stuff like that.
Al: They're mostly like Stardew,
Al: but you can put more than one in at a time.
Al: So you can put in up to 10 of anything that's generating,
Al: like you've got your kegs,
Al: you've got the mill for making.
Chelsea: The Mel, yeah. Beer. Oh, flowers.
Al: to write. Flour, that's what I'm looking for, flour and stuff like that. So any of these
Al: things that are like automated machines you can put in up to 10 at a time rather than just one,
Al: which is nice because it's much, much less babysitting of them than there is in Stardew
Al: where you had to live like here's my 20 different mayonnaise machines and you have to like run up it,
Al: put one egg in every machine and then back down. So it feels a lot less, you know, frustrating.
Chelsea: Yeah. Is there a way to speed them up a bit as the game progresses? Or no?
Al: I don't think so. I've not, not that I'm aware of, but I think as you progress on it's,
Al: it's less of an issue because just like things end up happening more anyway because you're,
Al: you're doing more stuff, right? Like I had, I have in my most recent spring and summer I had,
Al: oh, how many was it? Let me just do the maths. I had 480 crops.
Al: And in summer they were mostly grapes. And so because I staggered them, I just always
Al: had my kegs running with wine in them. Yeah, I don't think it's, I think because of like the
Chelsea: Yeah, that's kind of what I'm doing, I have the grapes and I'm just making mine.
Al: size of your farm and everything, I don't think you're ever going to get to the point where you
Al: have too many crops for your stuff and if you...
Al: end up with too many grapes for your wine then just grow something else instead because
Al: like the museum, one of the parts of the museum is having a two-star crop of every... two-star
Al: version of every crop, so it's like you're always wanting to grow something else. So
Al: I don't think that's a big problem.
Chelsea: Okay. I feel like I just don't have enough to do. Like, I'm basically just, like I said, I'm in the mines, getting ore, getting iron, getting copper, trying to... yeah, and fishing. Yeah.
Chelsea: So yeah, I feel like I'm just trying to, I guess, level everything up now so it's a little bit easier later on. But you don't have to play that way, that's just how I play.
Al: Yeah. Yeah. So I think that's all the farming stuff. There's ranching, obviously you've
Al: not experienced that because you're building up for your barn. Yeah, so most of the animals
Chelsea: I just bought my first chick, sorry, chicken. C H E E K.
Al: are like a normal animal but slightly different. So the chickens are chickens and they're just
Al: like they're black instead of normal chicken.
Chelsea: And they have their googly eyes
Al: They look a little bit dumb. The cows are, let me, give me a minute, let me get the actual names up.
Chelsea: I feel like a drought cowl or something like that.
Al: Cowcula, that's what they were called, yes. So there's Cowcula, they're basically just a cow,
Chelsea: Okay.
Al: but they have wings on, they have little wings on their back. You've got Draculamb,
Al: which is obviously a sheep, and it works pretty much the same way.
Al: You get wool from it.
Al: You can also get milk from them as well.
Al: So you get different types of milk.
Al: But the fun thing about the Draculambs is,
Al: oh, maybe I should,
Al: they're quite interested in revolution.
Al: They are always, hmm.
Al: Wait, are you aware that when you're in cat form,
Al: you can talk to animals?
Chelsea: No? Oh my god. Game of the year.
Al: Okay, when you're in cat form,
Al: you can talk to animals, which is super fun.
Al: So when they're on your farm,
Al: you can talk to them and they will tell you
Al: how happy they are.
Al: Whereas when you're a human and talk,
Al: or a vampire in human form, and you're talking to them,
Al: you get happy Draculamb noises.
Al: So you get an idea that it's happy,
Al: but you're not quite sure why.
Al: Whereas if you go into cat form,
Al: they'll be like, oh, I'm not liking,
Al: like, I don't have any food.
Al: or they might be like, "Oh, I don't like being."
Al: being in the same barn as this other animal
Al: or something like that.
Al: They'll give you reasons why they're unhappy
Chelsea: Oh, interesting. It's amazing.
Al: when you're in cat form, which is really fun.
Al: And if you talk to the Draculambs,
Al: you will find out that they're very interested
Al: in the concept of revolution
Al: and, you know, overthrowing their oppressors
Al: and stuff like that.
Al: And it's very interesting.
Al: And there's some story about that that happens as well,
Al: which is very fun that maybe I'll talk about in the spoilers section
Chelsea: Yes. Oh, yeah, because I just had my first, I just bought my first chicken, so I haven't had a chance to even talk to it yet.
Al: nice nice nice so then there's a pig goat which is kind of just like a weird looking
Chelsea: That's cool. I love that.
Al: goat with horns and they give you uh they give you milk as well a third type of milk
Chelsea: That's a lot. Oh dear.
Al: and then there then there's a bumpkin which is a sentient pumpkin which is very expensive they cost
Al: $12,000 and they give you what's called
Al: plops which very much looks like a poo and it has exactly one usage and that is
Al: to turn wheat into moonshine and then the next one is possibly my
Chelsea: [laughs] Amazing.
Al: favorite animal it's the stony it is a giant stone with lots of eyes and they
Chelsea: - Okay.
Al: give you heart stones which I think the only point of them is
Al: just giving you stone so you can in the refiner you can turn one heart stone
Al: into 20 stone I think that's the whole point but they are very fun to talk to I
Al: won't spoil everything but they're they're fun to talk to in cat form
Chelsea: Awesome.
Chelsea: I'm excited.
Chelsea: See, my thing with the pumpkin is like, can you carve it?
Chelsea: And it's like screaming the whole time.
Al: No, no you cannot
Chelsea: Probably not.
Chelsea: Oh, good.
Al: There is also apparently there's also apparently a
Chelsea: Okay.
Chelsea: Feel free to cut that out of the show.
Al: Rubicula, I have never encountered these in game. I didn't realize until
Al: Now that they were a thing you could do which is interesting
Al: So there you go
Al: They will give you luck dust apparently, which is a potion ingredient
Al: So you can use that in the love potion
Al: but apparently the the Rubicula's will also eat your crops if you let them so you gotta
Al: You've got a fence them in which reminds me
Al: Fences are fun in this game, but there are no
Al: Gates, there are no gates to put into the fences in this game
Chelsea: Yeah, no, I just have the haystack so far.
Al: It's very annoying because you can create a nice long fence with no gate in it
Al: It's not a problem now because I have the final form that I can use to
Al: bypass gates but it's very annoying early on and having a fence that you
Al: then have to like manually take down to move past or like it's just it just it's
Al: such a bizarre decision that there's no gates in this game
Chelsea: I wonder if they just couldn't get the physics of it or something.
Al: I don't care don't release the game until that it's not a difficult
Chelsea: Give me gates, gates, gate.
Al: all right that's mostly ranching that kind of work the same way you give them
Al: crop, you give them fodder, they...
Al: give you stuff. You pet them, they get happy, they give you bigger stuff. Great, fine.
Al: Fishing! Let's talk about fishing. What do you think about the fishing?
Chelsea: mm-hmm I don't mind it I only have the first rod because the second one is 16 000 gold
Chelsea: um so i'm catching the smaller stuff but I see the bigger figures in the water
Chelsea: but yeah I don't mind it like you can reel it in I think two or three times um I like it what about
Al: Yeah, so I guess just to give a quick explanation of how it works, it's kind of like the Animal
Al: Crossing one but slightly different. So you have, you throw or you cast your line into
Al: the water and then you see some shadows and if the shadow notices it, then it will go
Al: for it and then after a certain number of times it'll grab onto it and then you just
Al: it comes to you. The couple of things that make it, you can, so instead of just pressing
Al: the button to fully reel it in, if you don't have a fish on it, you just like tap it and
Al: it will move slightly. So it's like sometimes if the fish hasn't noticed the line, you can
Al: like tap it, tap the button and it'll pull it slightly and then they'll be like, the
Al: fish will notice you and come and be like "oh hello" and then it'll grab on, which you
Al: you kind of have to do. And then the bigger ones, there are two different
Al: size shadow sizes and you can only get the big shadow size with the more
Al: expensive rod. So it's not particularly difficult. Say again.
Chelsea: Yeah that seems like a late unlock. That seems like a late unlock though with the price of it.
Al: Yeah yeah yeah. Certainly medium game. It's not it's not insane. You can build
Al: up the money reasonably quickly mid game but yeah. There's not really a huge
Al: amount of skill to the fishing. Like if you if you hold down the button it will
Al: come and you're done, there's nothing.
Al: It's not particularly difficult.
Chelsea: Yeah, no, I don't think I've had anything let go or anything.
Al: Yeah, if you just don't press the button then it doesn't come but then like
Al: press the button. What's next on my list because I don't have my list in front of
Al: me because I'm an idiot. Mining! So mining, it's pretty self-explanatory. You have
Chelsea: Catching up mining
Al: the pickaxe, you see a rock, you hit it, you get something. Done.
Chelsea: That is a task and a half at the start.
Al: [laughing]
Al: - Yes, yeah, it takes a lot of energy to start with.
Al: But over time, you can decrease that
Al: with the higher pickaxes.
Chelsea: Yeah I think I'm just at the, I have two copper tools right now and I don't see a huge difference
Al: Nice.
Chelsea: but I see the upgrades.
Al: No, no, no.
Al: To start with, again, with the scaling,
Al: like I don't think until the final one
Al: you really notice that you're taking fewer hits.
Al: At that point, you've got a lot of mana
Al: and you just use the ethereal pickaxes
Al: to automatically do it.
Al: So by the time you've maxed that one out,
Al: two mana will break 48 rocks, that's a lot.
Chelsea: wow okay that's something to look forward to
Al: You can just walk through the mine and it kills everything
Al: and you just grab everything up, it's great.
Chelsea: perfect because i'm spending days and days and days in that mind
Al: Yeah.
Al: This is the real advantage of the magic being
Al: the automation is that you can then expand that to other areas in the same way, in that
Al: the same way you automatically water is also the same way you automatically get rocks and
Al: gold and stuff, and the same way that you can cut down trees, and the same way you move
Al: buildings because there's a spell for moving buildings, and the same way you can make it
Al: rain tomorrow, right? There's quite a few different spells that are quite good.
Al: Although, we're still limited by the mana, which I still think is very limited. I would have liked to have done more magic early on in the game, and even mid-game. It wasn't until late-game that I felt like I had enough mana to do everything that I wanted.
Chelsea: Oh, okay. Well, there's hope on the horizon then, 'cause I'm- I'm wasting away in that mine, honest to God.
Al: Next we have catching so there's bugs around and you can catch the bugs. This is not like
Al: your standard catching where you have to like sneak up on bugs and then press the button
Al: to catch them without them noticing you. You walk towards a bug it runs away from you and
Al: you have to chase it. Nope nope nope.
Chelsea: See, I didn't know if I was doing it wrong because I thought there was a way to be stealth about it
Chelsea: and then every time I run away and I'm like, "well, I guess I'm just racing it now!"
Chelsea: Okay, I thought, yeah, I thought I was doing it wrong.
Chelsea: Okay, good to know.
Al: There is no subtlety to it. You walk towards it, it runs away from you, you chase it, you
Al: chase it into a corner and you grab it. Done. The other thing you can catch is… have you
Chelsea: Yep, yep, yep.
Al: unlocked the soul blobs yet? So one of the characters in the game is death and yeah well
Chelsea: Yes, yes.
Chelsea: On vacation!
Al: how long is a vacation if you're there forever. One of the things…
Chelsea: [laughs]
Chelsea: He's got his Hawaiian shirt on!
Al: that death will do is ask you to get the soul blobs. Basically they are little skulls flying
Al: around with a little kind of like flame behind them and they are the souls of dead people
Al: and you have to catch them the same way you catch bugs and when you catch one it will
Al: give you a little bit very quick story as to how this person died. It will give you some
Al: examples because they are very fun. Playful tester died… cause of death…
Al: fell down the stairs… um… *laughs*
Chelsea: there's an animal crossing one I haven't caught it myself but there's one it's like thomas nook it's
Chelsea: like something about a landlord
Al: Oh, yeah, yeah, Yasmine Timely, cause of death, lost at poker against the Grim Reaper.
Chelsea: yeah
Al: Tom Finn, cause of death, they took his dog.
Chelsea: oh here it is thomas nook um cause of death evicted the wrong tenant
Al: Yeah, so there's quite a few good fun ones. Maria Doolong hugged a cactus.
Chelsea: I love that yeah all the blurbs are funny died setting an example
Chelsea: yeah
Al: So they're quite fun. I've got 92 of 100 of the soul blobs, so I'm actually nearly done that one.
Al: Maybe I'll finish that, we'll see. But it's just a fun little collectible, that's really all.
Al: I think after you get certain numbers of them you unlock certain things.
Chelsea: Yeah, I think I've done 10 or 15, and I got something at 10. I can't remember what it was.
Al: I think that's what it is. Weird thing to lock behind story progression, but you get
Chelsea: Oh yeah, you get the clock, the antique clock.
Chelsea: Yeah, that's what I've got so far.
Al: it quite quickly. So I'm not, it's not the same as like when Pokemon locked behind, you
Al: story progression, the ability to change the volume of the game.
Al: It's not as bad as that. So I don't know. I honestly don't know how I feel about it
Al: because I personally have never changed the speed of the days in these games because I've never felt
Al: like I need more time and I don't care about them going faster because I can just go to sleep.
Chelsea: See, I don't know if I ever- I thought I just kind of automatically applied it
Chelsea: because I haven't interacted with the clock. I put it out of my room, but I haven't activated it if you-
Al: don't interact, it just shows up in your settings after you have the clock. You don't even need
Chelsea: Oh, oh my god. Okay, because I was looking at this thing like, how do I turn it on?
Al: to put it out. No, it's literally, it just adds a setting in your settings.
Chelsea: Oh, okay. Okay, okay. But yeah, you're not like in an enormous rush unless you're traveling across the map.
Al: No. And even then, you speed up and you have other ways to do it. It's not, I don't, I've
Al: never really cared. I mean, some people do care, and that's fine. And so I don't know
Al: how they would feel about this being locked behind story progression. Because it's not
Al: an accessibility thing, right? You just get more time in the day to do stuff. So I don't
Al: think I care about it from that aspect. But also, why is it locked behind? I don't know.
Al: I don't care, I think.
Chelsea: Yeah, and then you also don't get penalized for like the amount of days you sleep and the amount of days that you start over, there's no penalty. Well, I guess it makes your season shorter.
Al: that's it yeah that's an interesting point to I haven't figured out where this goes in the
Al: in the discussion but two seconds I'm going to sneeze but one thing that's interesting is
Al: so in Stardew and most other farming games if you get to the end of the day and you haven't
Al: gone to bed you will wake up in the morning with less than your full stamina if you get to
Chelsea: Okay, yeah, it's 6 a.m.
Al: is it 6 a.m I think when you you just
Al: you just you turn it you turn into bats you fly to your bed and then the next day
Chelsea: You turn into bats and fly to your bed.
Al: you just have your full stamina there's no disadvantage to it and you know what I really
Al: like that because this is meant to be a cozy game give me more cozy like that like don't
Al: penalize me for staying out too late I i like this I really like this especially especially
Al: because of the like the story behind all this like you're a vampire and so like it doesn't
Al: really matter. You're not sleeping because you need to sleep, you're sleeping because
Al: you don't want to be awake when it's sunlight hours. And so it's like thematically, it makes
Chelsea: Yeah, I like that you're not penalized for that.
Chelsea: Yeah, 'cause I don't like when you, in other games, yeah, like you said Stardew, or I think Harvest Moon, if you collapse
Al: Take basically all of them.
Chelsea: at the end of the day, yeah, you wake up less energized, and I thought that was what was gonna happen, so I was racing at 5am, racing back to my bed,
Chelsea: and then I missed it, and you just kind of fly into your little room,
Chelsea: and you wake up in your coffin, and there's no penalty for that, that I've noticed, I don't think there is.
Al: There is yeah, there's nothing there's nothing
Al: The other collectible in the game is called vampsters. Have you encountered the vampsters?
Chelsea: Yeah.
Al: They're they're just little creatures that sit around the map doing a little dance and
Al: They're kind of cute. They all have like different costumes and stuff like that
Al: but the I
Al: Don't dislike them in concept, but my problem with them is they become very
Al: And they're still annoying at endgame so I
Chelsea: Oh no.
Al: Can feel I'm I'm getting more and more stuffed up as this podcast goes on
Chelsea: Oh no, my allergies have been sending your way.
Al: so
Al: I'm saying I'm probably sounding worse and worse as the podcast goes on, but I'm gonna keep going. We're getting there. We're nearly there
Al: um
Al: So the the thing about them that makes them annoying but also makes them an interesting
Al: Thing is that you can't put them in the bag. You have to like pick them up and take them to where they live
Al: from one side of the map to the other
Al: Without putting them down because if you put them down
Al: They've run away and they go back to where they were. So it's it's a
Al: Challenging collectible. It's not just like collect a thing. It's you have to get them to a specific place
Chelsea: I was so hoping that there would have been a spell where you can just drop them in the m- like, you like, summon them away.
Al: Yeah, so there's not. It does get easier, but there's one real thing that I dislike.
Al: Okay, so a little bit of a spoiler, very small spoiler for fast travel in this game. There
Al: are two kinds of fast travel. One is witch's circles, which are, there are certain areas
Al: that are like a circle of mushrooms and you can turn them into, yeah, yeah, yeah. So they're
Chelsea: Oh, I knew they did something!
Al: essentially like portals. They're fast travel. You go to one and you can teleport to a different
Al: Now, they have a little flaw in that there's not a huge number of them and there are awkward
Al: places, but you know what? It's fine. It is what it is. They're useful for certain things,
Al: but you cannot travel through them with a vampster.
Al: So that's, that's one thing. There is a second kind of fast travel, which is a better fast
Al: travel that you get later on in the game. I think it's 50% museum completion. And that
Al: is the catacombs. Catacombs. So there is a series of catacombs underneath the entire
Al: map. One of them is in your crypt, in your farm. And then there are various other parts
Al: throughout, including there is an entrance in the mines. So it's actually how the mines
Al: are, there's actually two mines. They're both connected through the catacombs. Now this
Al: is much better because you can just run through the catacombs with a vampster. And it's almost,
Al: It almost makes it not annoying in post game to do the
Al: The entrance to the mines is where you have to get them to the little cave in the mines right at the start of the mines, which is where you take the vampsters to is there is the other side of the mine from the entrance to the catacombs
Al: So if you find a vampster in the town, you go to the entrance to the catacombs, I won't spoil where that is, you go to the entrance of the catacombs, it didn't take you long, you get into the catacombs
Al: It didn't take you long, you run to the mines in the catacombs, didn't take you long, you are now on the other side of the mines from where you need to be and you have to run all the way from one end of the mines to the others, which takes longer than the rest of the journey you just did with your vampster
Al: Why is it so far away from this place? I am at the post game, I have done almost everything in this game, I have so many vampsters to get, they are deliberately annoying
Al: But right at the end of the game you would expect things to get easier and they do a little bit, but not enough because the thing is, see if I was just running across the map and going into the mines to put my vampsters away, it's right at the start of the mines
Al: So you are actually making it harder to get the vampsters to there by using that because you are the other side of the mines, now it speeds up everything else but it massively increases the time in the mines
Chelsea: Yep
Al: And the problem with the mines compared to everything else is there are so many obstacles because there's just rocks everywhere so it can take a huge amount of time
Al: And so I think the thing is that like, I get that they are meant to be a challenge and I don't dislike that but I feel like by the time you get to the end of the game and you've done the entire story and you've done everything else
Al: You've unlocked all of the catacombs, you're like more than 50% of the museum, you've done so much of this game
Al: So far away from where the vampsters are, it's bizarre to me, it's so close to being, yes, well that's the thing, that's exactly it, like finding them all and moving them there, I get that's a challenge
Chelsea: Yeah, tedious doesn't mean difficult.
Al: And like early on you don't want it to be too easy, I get that, but when I've done everything else, make the entrance to the catacombs in the mines closer to where the vampsters go
Chelsea: That needs to be the episode title of this episode. Why are the catacombs so- or why is the cave so far away?
Chelsea: Okay, yeah, 'cause I was thinking, "Oh, maybe- maybe you get a spell to just send them back in."
Al: Nope
Chelsea: Glad to hear you don't!
Al: So close so close
Chelsea: So close. I wonder if that's, like, an oversight on their part. Like, "Oh my god, we didn't put another entrance."
Al: I think it's I think it's just that they wanted
Al: The Vamsters to be difficult
Al: Full stop and never be easy and it's like but that kind of defeats the purpose of progression in games is the things generally are
Chelsea: It is easy, it's just a no-
Al: Meant to get easier unless it's specific about skill and this is not about skill
Chelsea: Yeah, that's the frustration.
Chelsea: No, 'cause you can bump into stuff, right? You just can't drop them.
Al: right
Al: Yeah, no, absolutely it just takes ages it just takes so long
Chelsea: Yeah.
Chelsea: 'Cause I was worried at the start, like, "Oh, if I bump into something, it's gonna escape from my arms and run away."
Chelsea: But no, you can bump into stuff, so it's not even a skill of your, like, uh, movement or anything.
Chelsea: But yeah, side note, I am glad to hear that-
Chelsea: 'Cause I remember going through them and my husband was sitting next to me and I'm like,
Chelsea: "Oh, there's fairy rings! I bet they do something!"
Chelsea: So I tried to do a whole bunch of stuff in them and they did nothing.
Chelsea: So I'm glad that they do something in the future.
Al: Yeah, you unlock a spell to open them. So that's that's how you get to them.
Chelsea: Yeah, okay, that's good to know.
Chelsea: But yeah, they don't- they seem really in really weird places to put them though.
Al: They are, they are, they're quite, they're awkward. They're not as you, like there's not
Al: one on your farm. You have to go to the forest to get to the closest one and it's like the one in
Al: the town is like far away from everything else. It's just, they're just, they're just at annoying
Al: places, which is fine because it's not the only fast travel and it does
Al: speed you up in most cases. So I don't, I'm not going to complain about them
Al: too much. I'm fine.
Chelsea: Okay.
Chelsea: The Vampsters, however.
Al: The hamsters, goodness me. Alright, so I think that's most of the mechanics.
Al: Unless you're going to correct me and say that I've missed a mechanic. I
Al: think the only other mechanic to talk about is relationships.
Chelsea: Yeah, I think that's about it.
Al: Alright, relationships is mostly kind of your standard Stardew Lake feature
Al: where you give people gifts.
Al: You talk to them, and that increases their friendship.
Al: And then eventually, you end up in a relationship with them.
Al: And then eventually, at some point, you get married.
Al: That's kind of generally how it works.
Chelsea: Yeah.
Al: With a couple of changes.
Al: So, have you done any of this?
Chelsea: Yes.
Chelsea: Yeah, I had the first, like, Valentine's Day festival, I guess.
Chelsea: Yeah, yeah, there's one that I think I'll choose.
Al: You'll choose I think they have a good. I think they have a good balance of
Chelsea: Yeah, if they choose me back!
Al: Younger and older characters, I think in this game. We're
Chelsea: Yeah, some of them I'm like, "You're a child."
Al: Yeah, but they also have some some ones that are clearly old like there's some that are the age of your parents in game
Al: Which means that people who are playing it have someone who's older
Al: I have seen a lot of people now, obviously my opinion is obviously very
Al: Kind of based on the fact that I am not generally attracted to men at all
Al: But I have generally found that
Al: the women are more
Al: Interesting and attractive but the internet seems to generally agree with me as well
Al: Which is why I don't think it's just that I'm not generally interested in men
Al: I think that the internet generally seems to agree with me
Chelsea: No, the women, yeah, 'cause the women have more, yeah, they're definitely more mythical looking, I'll say.
Al: But also every every man
Al: Every man that is in our that is really
Al: romanceable
Al: pines for a woman in the game
Al: Which like imagine if everyone was Clint, right?
Al: Like all of them are if you talk to because like I've obviously not romanced any of them
Al: But I've noticed they're clearly pining for the women in the game and I'm like if I was interested in them
Al: I would find that very frustrating
Chelsea: Yeah. Yeah, that's fair.
Chelsea: Have you, so you haven't thought of anyone that you wanna...
Al: Oh, yeah, you know, so I I have
Al: so I
Al: Got to the point where I had let's double-check. I've got it's been so long since I played this game. I have one two three
Al: four
Al: Four different characters that I'd gotten to the point where I could marry them
Al: Because you can date multiple people at the same time
Al: And I'll come back to that in a minute
Al: But what a really nice thing about this game is you can like duplicate a save
Al: So what I did was I finished the story
Al: I had everyone at the point where I could marry them.
Al: And then I saved and I duplicated that save so I can now go into each of those saves and marry
Al: each of those characters, which is fun. So I can see how they all are as spouses.
Al: One thing I really like about this is that if you do date multiple people, so obviously there's a
Al: thing in Stardew where if you date all of the datables of one gender that they will all come
Al: together and there's like a scene where they're all like "why are you dating us all?"
Al: But that's the only thing in Stardew about that. You can still date, you can date all bar one of
Al: them and nothing will ever come of that. What I really like about this game, yeah yeah, what I
Chelsea: We have to have a meeting about you.
Al: really like about this is the moment you start dating two characters they will both start
Al: mentioning the fact that you're dating other people. They won't do too much about it, it
Al: doesn't actually negatively impact, it's just like they will talk about it, right? So one of the
Al: characters was talking about it in a very...
Al: almost derogatory way, like, "I can't believe you're also dating them," sort of thing, like,
Al: "How could you consider them?" sort of thing. One of them was, "Oh, I'm a little bit upset,
Al: but I'm just going to have to learn to live with it if that's what you want," sort of
Al: thing. Like, they all had different ways of talking about it, and, you know, I thought
Al: that they all fit with their personalities. Like, one of them was just, like, completely
Al: upset, how I can't believe you would do this, I want you.
Al: which it doesn't actually affect the relationship, it just happens in conversation, you'll just be
Al: talking to them and they'll suddenly say that and you're like oh goodness okay.
Chelsea: Get coffee.
Al: So I thought that was really interesting and then when you choose to marry one of them,
Al: the rest of them are upset and they turn into a specific relationship status called hurt
Al: and they will drop back down to four hearts and all the hearts are broken.
Chelsea: Oh.
Chelsea: Oh, no.
Al: And they will not talk to you for a certain period of time including the ones that run shops
Chelsea: Oh, oh, my God.
Al: will not sell you anything until you recover the relationship to be friends again.
Chelsea: Oh, you can't get your stuff.
Chelsea: Wow, that's an interest, that's really interesting, I was
Chelsea: wondering if that was going to happen, like if there was any
Chelsea: negative effects.
Chelsea: Wow.
Al: And so the different ones will do different things,
Al: and some of them recover quicker than others
Al: and stuff like that.
Al: So I'm kind of going through my four different saves
Al: to see how they all react to that,
Al: which is, in my opinion.
Chelsea: Yeah, yeah, like to me the dating part's the least interesting aspect for me.
Chelsea: Yeah, I know who I'm gonna pick though, I don't know if I can say it here.
Al: - Tell me.
Chelsea: Ridge!
Al: Okay, fair enough.
Chelsea: The lumberjack, the lumberjack!
Al: Fair enough, yeah, no, that's fair enough.
Chelsea: He's so nice! He fixes your house for you, your roof for you, and seems like overall positive D.
Al: Yeah, yeah.
Al: Fair enough.
Chelsea: I almost did Luna though. Is that the the garden girl?
Al: Yeah, I like Luna, I just,
Al: I didn't quite gel with her as much
Al: as some of the other ones, but she was,
Al: I think if there hadn't been anyone
Al: I had liked more than her,
Al: then I definitely could have seen something there,
Al: but I wasn't.
Al: And I already had four people on the go. I was like, there's a lot here. Like, I don't
Al: think I need a fifth one sort of thing. So the four that I have been dating are Sabrina,
Chelsea: Okay. Right.
Al: Mina, Fiona, which is really awkward. Turns out Fiona is actually Sabrina's aunt. So that's
Al: a little bit awkward. Yeah.
Chelsea: What?!
Chelsea: Really?!
Chelsea: Ugh!
Al: Also Kim, but you won't have met Kim yet. No, that would be weird. That would be your
Chelsea: No, not yet.
Chelsea: Is it Kim Dracula?
Chelsea: No, okay.
Chelsea: Little bit.
Al: own family. Because you're a Dracula, remember? No, she is of a different type of character
Chelsea: Oh, okay, never mind.
Chelsea: Yes, okay, disregard.
Chelsea: Feel free to crop that out there.
Al: that you've not met yet that you might have theorized might exist. Although I'm just about
Chelsea: Okay, okay, okay, yeah, yes, okay.
Al: to talk about the fact that those characters exist in a second.
Al: uh so yeah it's fine it's not there's nothing humongously interesting I think the relationship
Al: between them is the most interesting thing but um overall it's kind of just pretty standard uh
Al: so obviously story-wise we don't want to talk about a lot of story because a lot of this is
Al: kind of like just as you go um but i've i've generally found the story quite interesting
Al: and fun it's not like overwhelmingly interesting but it is at least it makes me want
Al: continue doing things to find out and like you you know you learn through relationship building
Al: you get to know people and there's a lot of different characters that have different types
Al: archetypes and some of them feel a little bit kind of stereotypical but some of them actually
Al: find quite interesting like uh for the listeners one of the characters is alcoholic and him being
Al: an alcoholic actively...
Al: It impacts the story and people's relationships and is very interesting in ways that are hard
Al: to explain without explaining the story, but you really feel like his alcoholism affects
Al: everyone in the town.
Chelsea: Yeah. Yeah, even from the-- I haven't played nearly as much as you, but yeah, it has quite the impact already.
Chelsea: Like, you can see with his children and stuff.
Al: There's a bunch of different types of characters, so obviously we talked about vampires and
Al: witches, there's also werewolves. Ridges is a werewolf, I think, isn't he? Yeah. And then
Al: there's seers, and then the one that you unlock later on is there are merpeople that you will
Al: meet at some point, but I suspect you'd theorize that they existed. Yeah. And then there's
Al: also human characters that come later on.
Al: And then there's obviously kind of events that happen. There's like story events that happen where you kind of like how Stardew Works where you go to a certain area on a specific time and things happen. What I really like is the map shows you when there's an event going to happen if you go to a specific area, which is not, not all of these games do that.
Al: And I really like the fact that you can look in the map and say "Oh, that's a good map"
Al: if I go anywhere right now, will a thing happen, right?
Al: Because some things need very specific things to happen.
Al: So, like, for example, Kim, her 4Heart event had to happen at a specific time in a specific space.
Al: And if I hadn't been looking at the map at a specific time, I wouldn't have known that it was going to happen then.
Al: And I saw "Oh, there's a little sparkle on that map, let me go and see what happens"
Al: and it was Kim's 4Heart event, which was fun.
Chelsea: Oh, okay. Interesting.
Al: A couple of other things I found interesting but not.
Al: To a, not to a degree that I think would be great,
Al: there is one relationship that you do break up
Al: during the story, which is something I have asked for
Al: for ages, but is a specific one that you have to break up.
Al: So it's not like you're choosing to break up
Al: specific relationships to date someone,
Al: it's just, it's a thing that happens in the story.
Al: There, someone dies in this game, like properly dies.
Al: I'm not gonna tell you who,
Al: I'm not gonna give you any hints who,
Al: but someone dies in this game
Al: And I think it's--
Al: really well done what they do. They deal with grief in a very interesting way. I think it's very well done.
Chelsea: So I'm asking you after though.
Al: That's fine, you can ask me after.
Al: And then there's like, you know, festivals that happen. So that's a thing that happens.
Al: They're kind of standard. I don't think there's anything interesting to talk about them. If you
Al: know Stardew or you know any other kind of Stardew like, the festivals are exactly what you'd expect.
Chelsea: right. I'm pretty far behind. So no, I think no, I'm excited to
Al: Oh.
Al: Is there anything you want to talk about story and character wise that I've not talked about?
Al: Yeah, I know.
Chelsea: keep going, though, for sure. Yeah.
Al: I think the story was interesting enough. I don't think it quite hits the level of Stardew,
Al: but I think there are points where it does. Like the grief aspect that I was talking about I think
Al: is really, really well done. I think it's as well done as any Stardew story. But most of it is kind
Al: of pretty kind of cookie cutter. Like, it's fine. It's it's
Al: serviceable, it's enjoyable, but you're not going to, like, give it an Oscar sort of thing.
Chelsea: Yeah, I know. Yeah, we picked the busiest time of year to play the fifth game because I feel like I have a lot I want to say, and I'm excited to play a lot more of it, which is good.
Chelsea: Because I find, you know, where I'm at in the game is where I'd be able to choose if I want to continue or not. So yeah, it's promising to see what else comes ahead of it.
Al: We can always do a follow-up episode if you've got more thoughts once you've done more of the game.
Chelsea: Oh yes, please. Yes, please.
Al: That is always an easy episode for me because I don't need to do anything except talk.
Al: All right I think that's everything in the game then let's do a quick, before the spoiler section,
Al: let's do a quick summary of how we feel about the game and whether we'd recommend it.
Al: I mean I've already done that right like I said at the beginning if you like the idea of
Al: stardew but you're a vampire, I think play the game.
Al: It's very well made and it's very enjoyable. It's nothing super special but it's good. I enjoy it.
Chelsea: I agree yeah I don't have anything else to add at that point but yeah no it's I'm enjoying it like I
Chelsea: I play a lot of Animal Crossing and this feels different enough that it's not Animal Crossing
Chelsea: but enough similar features that I don't feel like a complete stranger to this kind of game
Chelsea: so yeah I do enjoy it and I would recommend it.
Al: Nice all right well that is basically the entire podcast the only thing that
Al: we're gonna it's gonna be after this is a few spoilers that we mentioned
Al: throughout the episode so if you don't want to be spoiled for this then you can
Al: head out now there's nothing else after this go away spoiler warnings by the
Al: warning all right so I wrote the list as we were going you want to know who dies
Chelsea: [dog barking]
Al: we'll go with that first it's not Brooke dies Brooke
Chelsea: Sure, is it Orlok? No? Who does? No! Oh god. Yeah. Okay. Oh.
Al: the mayor
Al: it's actually a really touching story I won't spoil everything but he dies but
Al: the really funny thing is because he dies you then have to elect a new mayor
Al: and I won't tell you who wins but I will tell you one of the one of the candidates
Al: is a vampster
Chelsea: I got my vote. Wow, that's interesting.
Al: I bet you could probably guess who becomes mayor but I will neither confirm
Chelsea: I don't know. Okay, no, I'm not even gonna guess.
Al: nor deny. Yes, go on, guess, guess, guess, guess.
Chelsea: Is it Orlok? No, it's not.
Al: I've told you now they're going to confirm nor deny.
Chelsea: Okay, okay, I'll get to that myself.
Al: The transformation, so obviously the cat was the one you've had,
Al: what were you guessing was one of them? Because you had a theory. It is, yeah, yeah, correct.
Chelsea: It's, uh, is it a mermaid that can go in the water? Yeah, okay.
Chelsea: Yes, okay, I was like, there's way too much to explore out there to not have that ability.
Chelsea: Like, it...
Al: And the final one is a bat, which kind of makes sense.
Chelsea: Okay, yeah, I figured at some point you would eventually get your, like,
Chelsea: your wings and be able to just do that yourself. I do like the cat, though.
Al: Yeah, no, I actually, yeah, I think they're really good.
Chelsea: - Yeah, I love being, I see, I thought.
Chelsea: I thought that when I turned into a cat,
Chelsea: I could talk to my cat,
Chelsea: but he only talks to you like a person.
Chelsea: I thought he'd be like, I don't know.
Chelsea: That makes no sense because I realized
Chelsea: that he still talks to you even as a cat.
Chelsea: Disregard, disregard.
Al: and the bat is really fun because you're flying so you can fly over things.
Chelsea: He can talk to you either way.
Chelsea: Oh, is that how you get to the second level of the mind?
Chelsea: Okay, okay.
Chelsea: I was like, there must be a ladder recipe or something.
Al: The sunscreen potion. This is so stupid. The only purpose of this potion is so that you can talk to the sun god.
Chelsea: What? I thought it would just make you be able to lengthen your day.
Al: Nope, nope, it doesn't do that. So there's a character in the game called the sun god
Al: and there's a whole bunch of story stuff around that but basically to talk to him.
Al: That's it. That's it. That's the whole thing
Chelsea: I like my idea better. Make the day longer!
Al: Yeah, I also thought it would be that as well but it's not
Al: and the draculaams
Al: They do ferment a revolution in the game
Chelsea: Oh my god, I can't wait.
Al: It is I love the draculaam
Al: Revolution, I will not tell you what happens. I won't spoil it all but the revolution is super super fun
Chelsea: Okay. Is that way, way late in the game?
Al: No, no, it's kind of made it's kind of mid game
Chelsea: Oh, okay!
Chelsea: Perfect. I have all these things to look forward to now.
Al: So yeah, that's it. I think that's it. I think that's all the time we have for this episode
Al: Thank you for tuning in to the show
Chelsea: Thanks for having me, and we're glad you're back.
Chelsea: What? It's your show!
Al: All right, well, I think that's everything then thank you chelsea for joining me for this episode
Chelsea: Uh, play Moonlight Peaks.
Chelsea: Simple, just keeping it at that.
Al: Alright, you can find the podcast on Tumblr and on BlueSky at THSPod. You can also find
Al: us on YouTube where I am sharing a bunch of clips from the podcast. I'm trying to do one
Al: a day and some of them are gaining traction and interesting and if you enjoy that then
Al: that's there if you want to go and look at it. You can also send us feedback from our
Al: website HarvestSeason.Club where you can also find links to everything to do with the podcast
Al: including our Patreon, patreon.com/thspod, where you can...
Al: ...support the podcast monetarily, if you wish, and in return for some money on a monthly basis,
Al: you can get access to our Slack, where we talk about a bunch of things,
Al: what we've been talking about recently on there.
Al: Chelsea, you shared your picture of the bedazzled goose lamp.
Chelsea: If that's worth the money right there, to see that thing.
Al: Absolutely. Absolutely.
Al: You can try and convince me to play games that are clearly bad,
Al: and I can't decide whether I want to play or not.
Al: for the podcast that's a thing you can do.
Chelsea: Yes, because right now you're debating Harvest Moon port.
Al: Yes the terrible looking ports of terrible games that are on mobile
Al: and who knows why they've decided to do that.
Chelsea: Come bully Al into playing the Harvest Moonports.
Al: Please do.
Al: You also get access to bonus episodes of the podcast and now that I'm back
Al: from my holiday we should be getting a bunch of them up.
Al: I know Codey promised about 10...
Al: in their last episode. So...
Chelsea: Yes.
Chelsea: Yeah, me and Kevin have a list, too.
Al: I mean, you just need to actually start recording them then. Come on.
Al: Like, you people keep promising greenhouses and not actually doing them. So...
Chelsea: Oh, me and Kevin have a date set for one. Thank you. Yes.
Al: Good. Good. Get it done.
Al: So there will be, hopefully, quite a few over the next couple of months as I
Al: try and get to an arbitrary number that I want to do within a calendar year.
Al: Woo!
Al: All right. That's everything. Thank you, Chelsea, for joining me.
Al: Thank you, listeners, for listening. And until next time, have a good harvest.
Chelsea: Have a good harvest.
Theme Tune: The Harvest Season is created by Al McKinley with support from our Patrons including our
Theme Tune: Pro Farmers Kevin, Stuart and Elisa. Our art is done by Micah the Brave and our music is
Theme Tune: done by Nick Burgess. Feel free to visit our website HarvestSeason.club for show notes
Theme Tune: and links to things we discussed in this episode.
Al: seconds. Hey Google, turn on the light. I didn't realize I was sitting without lights
Al: on and it's starting to get dark. So I was like, I can't see things anymore.
Chelsea: [laughs]
Chelsea: Wait, I can't see anything.
Al: Um, fair.